So today's דף daf *Daf* is ס *Samech*, 60, and we are
finally going to finish this long discussion about the what do you
call it about the onion, the
onion
that keeps on growing and what its status is. So ש *sh*,
we look at the top pick up at the very bottom of
נט עמוד amud ב *Nun Tet Amud Bet*, גופא *Guffa*, we'll go
back to what we said earlier, אמר Amar, רבי חנינא *Amar Rabbi
Chanina*, צירטם רב ינאי בצלים של תרומה terumah שנטעו ורבו גידוליו על
עיקרו מותר mutar. *Tzirtam Rav Yanai betzalim shel Terumah sheneta’o verabu gidulav
al ikaro mutar*. You have an onion of תרומה terumah, *Terumah* that
you planted it and now the stuff that has grown has larger
than the amount that was originally there, מותר mutar *mutar*, it is
permissible cause the original stuff is מבטל *mevatel* the עיקר ikar, *ikar*.
So that was our primary focus along. Do you say that ביטול
bitul. *bitul* works or not? And you know again the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* proved that it worked by שמיטה shmitah *Shemitah*, maybe שמיטה shmitah
*Shemitah* is an exception. But anyway now we're sort of working with
the assumption that the new stuff that grows does do ביטול bitul,
*bitul*, the only recent question was maybe does it even מבטל *mevatel*
היתר *heter* and turning היתר *heter* into איסור *issur*? That was the
fascinating question yesterday. But anyway here's a statement that it does do
ביטול bitul? *bitul*. Now we're going to ask a question we probably
should have asked two days ago. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says למימרא
Lemimra, *le-meimra*, this suggests דגידולי היתר מעלין את האיסור *de-gidulei heter ma’alin
et ha-issur* that yes the stuff that grows the היתר *heter* is
מבטל *mevatel* the original amount which was איסור *issur*, top of of
ס *Samech*. והתנן ve-hatnan, *ve-hatnan*, but we taught in the משנה Mishna?
*Mishna*, גידולי תרומה terumah תרומה terumah. *gidulei Terumah Terumah*, that the stuff
that grows from תרומה terumah, *Terumah*, forget a question of ביטול bitul
*bitul*, the stuff that grows from תרומה terumah, *Terumah* is itself considered
to be תרומה terumah. *Terumah*. So if it's itself considered to be
תרומה terumah, *Terumah*, the stuff that grows by virtue that it grew
from it, forget any question of ביטול bittel. *bitul*, right? So anything
that grows from the thing is like the thing itself. So how
does this whole conversation begin? And you were even if you say
that maybe that's only in certain categories, but he was talking about
תרומה terumah, *Terumah*. So you know the whole thing is like what
have we been talking about ביטול bittel, *bitul*? Maybe the stuff that
grows from it is like the thing itself and we see that's
true by תרומה terumah *Terumah*. So he said, it doesn't matter, we're
focusing on his statement about תרומה terumah. *Terumah*. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says בגידולי גידולין אמרינן *begidulei gidulin amrinan*. Okay, so it's a
real knockout question and it says his statement, this statement of רבי
חנינא *Rabbi Chanina* was talking not about the stuff that grew from
the the thing that originally was תרומה terumah *Terumah* and continued to
grow, it's talking about the third generation, not the second generation. Something
grew from which from something that had grown. Now the problem with
this is that you can understand גידולי גידולין *gidulei gidulin* if you're
talking about something like wheat. You take the seed, you plant it,
then that's considered the גידולין *gidulin*, then you take the seed of
what has grown and you plant it, that's the גידולי גידולין *gidulei
gidulin*, right? So that you can have a third generation and then
you could say the third generation is no longer תרומה terumah *Terumah*.
How exactly do you get that by case of an onion is
a lot less clear. You have your onion it continues to grow
that's גידולין *gidulin*. What's the גידולי גידולין *gidulei gidulin*, right? You don't
take like a slice of that onion and you plant it, right?
Do you? I don't think so. So is maybe you pull it
out of the ground and you plant it back in the ground?
Something like that. Okay it's hard to understand exactly what the scenario
shoots
if you let them stay for too long, so
maybe take that shoot, plant it in the ground. Is that how
it works?
Like on פאה *Pe’ah* there's הברכה *havrachah* like you know they...
Alright maybe, I don't know exactly how it works. Anyway so he
said that's what we're talking about. All along we thought we were
talking about the stuff that grew, no we're actually talking about the
third generation because by תרומה terumah. *Terumah* the second generation really is
תרומה terumah *Terumah* itself. הא נמי תנינא *ha nami tanina*, so the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says but okay but we already know that. גידולי
גידולין חולין *gidulei gidulin chullin*, the third generation is חולין *chullin*. Now
that might be true but remember the חידוש chiddush *chiddush* of רבי
חנינא *Rabbi Chanina* was not just that what grew was חולין *chullin*
but that it was מבטל *mevatel*, negated the original thing, right? That
it you did ביטול bittel *bitul*. Okay but anyway the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara*'s going to just clarify this that there's a חידוש chiddush *chiddush*
in this branch as well. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says הכא קמשמע
לן Kamashma lan? אפילו בדבר שאין זרעו כלה *hacha kamashma lan afilu
bedavar she-ein zaro kalah*. Yes, but when do we say second generation
is תרומה terumah. *Terumah*, third generation is not תרומה terumah, *Terumah*? That's
something with like the seed of wheat that the seed disintegrates and
you really have something completely new. So in the regarding the second
generation that's a huge חידוש chiddush *chiddush*. The wheat that grew from
a seed that was תרומה terumah *Terumah*, even though the original seed
is no longer there, is itself considered תרומה terumah *Terumah*. That's a
huge חידוש chiddush *chiddush*, right? But then we say the third generation
of that is not תרומה Terumah, *Terumah*, okay, because that's really two
complete generations removed. Here we're talking about an onion. So on the
one hand the second generation certainly should be תרומה Terumah, *Terumah* in
this case if by wheat the second generation is תרומה Terumah *Terumah*
certainly by the onion. But there's but then but what we'll also
say is we'll be lenient when it comes to the third generation
just like we are by wheat. And that
the
third generation of the onion, even though some of the original thing
is still there, אין זרעו כלה *ein zaro kalah*, right? It's not...
so why have we even spending the last two days, yes, talking
about ביטול bittel, *bitul*? Now we're finally saying who the heck can
get to the conversation about ביטול bittel *bitul*? The stuff that continues
to grow by תרומה Terumah *Terumah* is itself considered תרומה Terumah *Terumah*.
And the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says that would not be true by
the third generation and we're talking about a case of the third
generation and even though it's all somehow a case that the original
thing is still there to some degree, אין זרעו כלה *ein zaro
kalah*, right? It's not... not like seeds that disintegrate, nevertheless by the
third generation the new stuff is not תרומה Terumah and therefore that
negates the original. So there's two חידושים, chiddushim, one is that the
new stuff is not תרומה Terumah and B that it negates the
original and it does do ביטול. And now the גמרא Gemara finally
concludes this discussion,
the גמרא Gemara says like this, והתנן, one minute, how can you
say that? Don't we teach in a משנה? Mishna הטבל גידוליו מותרים.
ha-tevel gidulav mutarin. טבל, tevel, not like תרומה, again it's very interesting.
Different categories of הלכה halacha whether the thing that grows from it
has the status or not is not always the same. Now then
we were completely ignoring that in our earlier conversation about that that
maybe the status would get transferred to what grew. So we said
by תרומה the second generation is תרומה. The משנה Mishna says that
by טבל, tevel, grain that does not have תרומות ומעשרות terumot u-ma'asrot
taken from it, what grows is מותר. Okay? Is okay. So it's
only a הלכה halacha about תרומה, right? By something very close to
תרומה, טבל, tevel, it does not apply to the second generation. So
that's an important חידוש chiddush number one. And then it says,
גידוליו מותרים בדבר שזרעו כלה. gidulav mutarin be-davar she-zaro kalah. That's by
wheat, something that the seed disintegrates. אבל בדבר שאין זרעו כלה, aval
be-davar she-ein zaro kalah, but something that the original seeds does not
disintegrate, okay, גידולי גידוליו אסורים. gidulei gidulav asurim. Even by טבל, tevel,
which is more lenient, that it doesn't pass on to the second
generation, more lenient than תרומה. Nevertheless, if it's something like an onion
that the original thing is still there, okay, it says that even
by טבל tevel that will continue to the third generation. Everybody with
me? So basically what we said is, if you've got your scenario
of an onion again before you can start talking about ביטול, if
you have your scenario of an onion then the second generation should
be תרומה, the third generation should be תרומה, should even be even
in a case of טבל tevel which tends to be more lenient
about passing on to another generation, it should continue to apply down
the generations or at least to the third generation. So how can
we even talk about ביטול? What grew should be תרומה because it's
not דבר שכלה, davar she-kalah, it's a case of the onion. And
therefore what keeps on growing should continue to be תרומה. So like
we've like total knockout of the park question here, which we waited
to the very end of the סוגיא sugya to ask. So let's
see why we've waited to the very end of the סוגיא. sugya.
Why would we wait the end of the generation? To what degree
is it a continuation of the original thing or not?
Is it תרומה as you said?
Oh, between תרומה and טבל? tevel? I don't know, but let's not
worry about that. So the גמרא Gemara says like this,
let me get ahead, but why spend two days with this and
then just make these assertions without any argument?
Yeah, I don't know, well, it's not without any argument, but like
why ask the bigger question at the end? How do we allow
the earlier question to proceed? Yeah, I don't know the answer to
that. I mean the גמרא's Gemara going to find a way out
of it. It's not, we'll see the answer, it's not going to
throw out everything it did the last two days, but it certainly
contextualizes everything in a very different way. So, but so I really
don't know why. You're right. I mean that's what I'm sort of
implicitly saying. This should have come right at the beginning. Okay? We
wouldn't have been as invested in the conversation the last two days
if this had come at the beginning. Let's see what the answer
is. Hold on, let's see the answer. The answer is, the גמרא
Gemara says, so אבל דבר שאין זרעו כלה גידולי גידולין אסורין. aval
davar she-ein zaro kalah gidulei gidulin asurin. The גמרא Gemara. says ריבוייא
דראבו גידולין על עיקרו מותר קמשמע לן. ribuya de-rabu gidulin al ikaro
mutar kamashma lan. Now that's a hard phrase to understand what it's
saying. It says the amount that it grew over the עיקר, ikar
that's permissible. Yeah, but that was our question. Our question was what's
the story about גידולי גידולים? gidulei gidulim? So the ר"ן Ran and
other ראשונים rishonim have a different גירסא girsa which they say more
or less means the same here. And if you take a look,
it's the ר"ן Ran on the previous עמוד actually. His גירסא girsa
is, הכי גרסינן, hachi garsinan, it's like six lines from the bottom,
התם דלא רבו גידולא על עיקרו. hatam d-lo rabu gidula al ikaro.
When do we say that the third generation by the onion is
forbidden? That's when you don't have a case of רוב. rov. אבל
הכא גבי ביטול של תרומה משום שרבו גידולי גידולים על הגידולים. aval
hacha gabi bitul shel terumah mishum she-rabu gidulei gidulim al ha-gidulim. So
what the ר"ן Ran says is we basically, we basically try to
get out of it. We say yes the evidence sounds like in
an onion case when the עיקר is there, even like third generation
is still תרומה. But we're going to say that's not what that
משנה Mishna meant. When the משנה Mishna. said third generation is תרומה
in the case of an onion, that's only when what continued to
grow in later generations is still a minority. It's not, it's not
בטל. batel. So it really wasn't saying that the third generation of
growth gets the status and is itself תרומה. What it's saying is
that the onion remains forbidden because you still have the original part
of the onion that's תרומה, right? Do you understand? When we say
the onion is forbidden, is it because what grew is also תרומה
or is it forbidden because you still have the original onion there?
You just have other stuff, but you also have the original onion.
So that's what it's saying. It's saying we're going to preserve our
idea that the stuff that grows is not תרומה and that you
can do ביטול as long as it's third generation let's say, not
second generation. How about that thing that says that when you've got
the original onion it still remains a problem? It still remains... טבל
tevel it still means תרומה, that's when there wasn't enough to do
ביטול. But when there's enough to do ביטול, then we're going to
say two things: number one is the new stuff that grew was
not תרומה, and number two that ביטול can work. Okay? So in
the end we managed to preserve the idea that the stuff that
grows is not תרומה and it can do ביטול, but we just
wound up saying that that would be talking about a case of
third generation, not second generation. So you see Seth we managed to
preserve everything we said before by manipulating some of this evidence and
saying that as long as you're dealing with third generation we can
still say what grows is not תרומה and that ביטול is possible.
Is it the same law as טבל tevel and תרומה then?
No, cause the question is still by something like the wheat that
you plant the seeds of the wheat, by תרומה the second generation
is תרומה and by טבל tevel it is not. Okay. All right.
Let us הדרן עלך הנודר מן הירק. Hadran Alach Hanodea Min Hayarak.
We are moving on. All right. Tactical question. Got to be very
short, yeah.
Is this an unusual use of קמשמע לן? Kamashma lan In other
words usually קמשמע לן Kamashma lan subverts shows the last thing you
just said is not true.
Yeah, so yes, I
mean in this קמשמע לן it's been established.
Yeah, or something like that, yes, which is also why some ראשונים
Rishonim have a different גרסא. girsa. Okay. Now we get to put
that whole onion behind us and move on to a much easier
פרק. perek. Let's get a move on. Kovam, thank you. קונם יין
שאני טועם היום. Konam yayin shani toem hayom. אינו אסור. Eino asur.
Now we remember we started talking about if you say I won't
eat grain or I won't eat this or whatever, how much what's
included I won't eat תבשיל, tavshil, you know, what type of food
are you talking about? What's included in that word that describes the
object, the food that you won't eat. Now we're talking about what's
included when you describe the duration. How should we interpret what that
duration means? Okay, so that's going to be the focus of this
פרק. perek. קונם יין שאני טועם היום, Konam yayin shani toem hayom,
I won't drink taste wine today. אינו אסור אלא עד שתחשך. Eino
asur ela ad shetechshach. So you go by the halachic day, it
doesn't mean twenty-four hours, you said today, so you are only forbidden
until it gets dark. So it's not permissible once the sun sets.
Regardless
of when you said it. You could say it a minute before
sunset.
Or at any point the night before.
Right, exactly, exactly. It goes by the halachic day, so it doesn't
become permissible at sunset, it becomes permissible when it's dark like when
the stars come out, okay, the halachic end of the day, that's
when it becomes permissible. And as Michael points out, that could be
five minutes, it could be twenty-five hours. Okay. שבת זו, Shabbat zu,
if you say I won't taste wine this שבת, Shabbat, this week,
okay, that's what שבת Shabbat means this week, אסור בכל השבת, asur
bechol hashabbat, you can't drink the whole week whether you're on Sunday
or on Friday or on שבת Shabbat itself. והשבת לשעבר Vehashabbat lesheavar
or it should be והשבת לשעבר, Vehashabbat lesheavar, meaning the שבת Shabbat
is considered to be part of the past week not
the beginning of the next week, okay, which is pretty obvious. So
if you're on Sunday and you say I won't drink this week
then it includes שבת. Shabbat. Okay, you don't say שבת Shabbat the
new week starts on Sunday or Saturday night. The new week, so
שבת Shabbat counts as part of the previous week. Okay, לשעבר. lesheavar.
Oh the word שבת Shabbat
here has two different meanings.
Yeah, the second שבת Shabbat here actually means שבת, Shabbat, correct. חודש
זה, Chodesh zeh, I won't drink taste wine this month, אסור בכל
החודש, asur bechol hachodesh, you can't drink the whole month, וראש חודש
להבא. verosh chodesh lehaba. But ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh is obviously not
the end of the month you're in, it's the beginning of the
next month.
Unless there's two-day ראש חודש.
Rosh Chodesh. Well, okay, so the גמרא'ס Gemara's going to say that's
pretty obvious, of course ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh the beginning of the
next month, so it's going to talk about a two-day ראש חודש.
Rosh Chodesh. Okay. שנה זו, Shanah zo, I won't taste wine this
whole the wine is forbidden to me this whole year, so אסור
בכל השנה, asur bechol hashanah, you can't drink the whole year, וראש
השנה לעתיד לבא, verosh hashanah leatid lavo, and ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah
begins the next year. That's even more obvious. So that's even more
obvious. So out again it's a question what the חידוש chiddush here
is. But שבת Shabbat is of the previous week, ראש חודש Rosh
Chodesh and ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah is of the next month and
of the next year. It is by the way interesting knowing the
different phrases here, it is interesting noticing the different phrases, that ראש
חודש Rosh Chodesh it says is להבא. lehaba. The ראש חודש Rosh
Chodesh counts towards the coming month להבא lehaba what's about to come.
ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah counts לעתיד לבא. leatid lavo. Okay, we always
are wondering about when is it going to be the you know
לעתיד לבא leatid lavo etc. לעתיד לבא leatid lavo is just already
ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah it's already לעתיד לבא. leatid lavo. Anyway but
presumably it's the future that is yet to come, presumably it's just
a little bit more distant than ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, than ראש
השנה. Rosh Hashanah. So ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh is the coming time
and ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah it's already the future because it's like
even more in the future. Okay. באחרית הימים. Beacharit hayamim.
Exactly. שבוע זה, Shavua zeh, this whole שבוע, shavua, now שבוע shavua
here means a שמיטה shmitah cycle, אסור בכל השבוע, asur bechol hashavua,
it's forbidden the whole שבוע shavua cycle, והשביעית שעברה, vehasheeit sheavrah, and
the שמיטה shmitah. year is the end of the previous cycle. So
it includes through the שמיטה Shmita year. The next cycle begins after
שמיטה. Shmita ואם אמר, Veim amar, but that's if you said this,
this day, this month, this week.
ואם אמר Veim amar יום אחד, yom echad, שבת אחת, shabbat achat,
חודש אחד, chodesh echad, שנה אחת, shanah achat, one
month, one
year, שבוע אחד, shavua echad, one... One seven-year period, אסור מיום ליום.
Asur miyom leyom. Then you go for a for a from day
to day, meaning if you're on Monday and you say one day
and you're at Monday at 1:00 PM, you go to Tuesday at
1:00 PM, you go a full 24 hours. If you're on Monday
and you say this week, then you go back to then you
go until next Monday, presumably also even at that same time, presumably
it would go even down to hours. Okay, if you say this
month and you're let's say, I don't know, on the third of
אדר, Adar, then not
this month, a month, right?
No, I'm sorry, a month. Thank you, thank you. Correct, correct. If
you say right, one so if you said if you're on Monday
and you said one week, then you would go until until next
week on Monday presumably on Monday until like to like a minute
before, you know, what what the the time you were at the
previous week. If you were said a month and you are let's
say on the, you know, on the third of אדר, Adar, so
you would presumably go until the third of ניסן, Nisan, you know,
till a minute before when you had said it. Again, that's not
so clear. Do you break it down? When you say a day,
clearly you go till like a minute before. When you say a
week or a month, do you go to like the day before
or do you go to like the minute before? That's I think
a little less clear in the משנה. mishna Okay, but then you
start
again and you say this month, right? Can't wait a month?
No, that's a good question. I mean that comes up a little
bit by a נדר, neder, but it's assumed to be that you
start right away. Okay, so here you go for the for the
full of duration until the time that you are standing in.
Okay. אסור מיום ליום. Asur miyom leyom. עד הפסח, Ad haPesach, if
you say I am forbidden to wine until פסח, Pesach, אסור עד
שיגיע, asur ad sheyagia, then you're forbidden until פסח Pesach begins. When
you say until, we assume it means עד ולא עד בכלל, ad
velo ad bichlal, until but not including. Okay, if you say עד
שיהיה, ad sheyehei, until until it becomes פסח Pesach or until פסח,
Pesach, so then we say what that means is אסור עד שיצא,
asur ad sheyetze, we mean until פסח Pesach is over. That's how
we read עד שיהיה, ad sheyehei, until it's the thing of the
past. Okay, so we read it until the end of פסח. Pesach.
עד פני Ad pnei is the גרסא. girsa. עד פני הפסח, Ad
pnei haPesach, until the face of פסח. Pesach. So רבי מאיר אומר
Rabbi Meir omer אסור עד שיגיע. asur ad sheyagia. The face means
the beginning of פסח, Pesach, so you're forbidden until פסח Pesach begins.
ורבי יוסי VeRabbi Yossi אומר omer עד שיצא. ad sheyetze. פני Pnei
means the sort of the the face at the back face of
it, not the front face of it. So it means until until
פסח Pesach is over. So there there's a debate. Okay, let's take
a look at the גמרא. Gemara קונם יין. Konam yayin.
It's odd that in the משנה mishna or so concerned with meanings
words, we don't consider שבוע shavua might be a week rather than
a.
Yeah, as opposed to שבת. Shabbat. שבת Shabbat and that. It's true,
it's true. You know, right. I mean presumably that's לשון בני אדם,
lashon bnei adam, but it is true, especially given that in the
משנה mishna itself, the meaning of שבת Shabbat switches from one line
to the next. You know. Yeah.
But my my משנה Mishna has עד פני הפסח. ad pnei haPesach.
Yeah, but if you look at the side, it says צריך לומר
tzarich lomar in the left-hand margin פני. pnei. וכן גרסת רש״י והר״ן
והרא״ש V'chen girzat Rashi vehaRan vehaRosh
etc.
פני Pnei is obviously before.
Right, yeah.
And a person have a נדר neder not to have wine on
פסח? Pesach?
Well yes, because a נדר, neder, since it's not a שבועה, shvua,
will indirectly like you can even say a נדר neder סוכות Sukkot
are forbidden to me. I understand, so then you would have to
not drink the four cups of wine. You'd have to either get
released from your vow or drink something you know else. But I'm
saying yeah, because נדרים nedarim work because they're not about actions, they're
about objects. They can work to indirectly subvert the performance of מצוות.
mitzvot. Like somebody could say, you know, קונם כל תפילין Konam kol
tefillin is forbidden to me, right? Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
קונם יין שאני טועם. Konam yayin she'ani to'em. אמר רבי ירמיה: Amar
Rabbi Yirmeyah: לכשתחשך, Lichshetechshach, once it gets dark. So if you say
today, it's permissible when it gets dark. So he says, okay, very
nice. But לכשתחשך, lichshetechshach, once it gets dark, צריך שאלה לחכם, tzarich
she'eila lechacham, you need to get a חכם chacham to מתיר matir
your נדר. neder. Which is funny, it got dark, the נדר neder
is over. So מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, what's the reason? אמר רב
יוסף: Amar Rav Yosef: גזירה היום משום יום אחד. Gzeira hayom mishum
yom echad. We're afraid that if you say today and it's permissible
come nightfall, then when you say one day, you'll also think it's
permissible come nightfall. Okay, so if you're standing here at 1:00 PM
on Tuesday and you say today, it's permissible at I don't know
7:00 PM. But if you said one day, it's forbidden until you
know 12:59 on Wednesday. So we're concerned that if we allow you
to when you say even when you say today to start drinking
at night, that's going to you know you're going to come to
treat when you say one day the same as when you say
today.
But if you said until 12:00 PM tomorrow it would be today,
then you wouldn't have any problem.
Correct. אמר ליה אביי: Amar lei Abaye: אי הכי, I hachi, ניגזר
יום אחד משום היום. nigzar yom echad mishum hayom. So let's make
a גזירה gzeira in the reverse. If you say one day and
you're at Monday at 1:00 PM, why we shouldn't let you drink
starting Tuesday at 1:00 PM? We should wait wait until Tuesday night.
Because if you start drinking in the middle of a day on
Tuesday, you'll think that even if you say today, you don't have
to wait until nightfall. Now there's an obvious big difference. Let's see
what the גמרא Gemara says
difference is. אמר ליה: Amar lei: היום ביום אחד מחלף. Hayom beyom
echad michlaf. Today with one day you could confuse. יום אחד בהיום
לא מיחלף. yom echad behayom lo michlaf. One day with today you
can't confuse. Now it doesn't say why, but תוספות Tosafot points out
the obvious difference. If I say today and I start, and I
stop drinking wine starting now until nightfall, okay, and then I'm permissible.
Then I could think that if I said one day, I'll stop
drinking wine from now until nightfall and I'll be permissible. That could
be confused, right? It was saying I went to a period of
not drinking wine and then it became permissible when nightfall occurred. But
think about the other case. I said one day. I don't drink
wine for twenty-four hours and then it's permissible. Fine. Now
instead I say today I won't drink wine. When am I going
to think it's going to become permissible? Now? Right? I haven't been
practicing the נדר. neder. There's no way that can lead to me
treating it like the other case unless it leads to me not
drinking twenty-four hours which also wouldn't be a problem. Okay, so you
don't have the same thing, right? The idea of one day is
longer than the idea of today. So if we're lenient, if by
today we let you do the shorter time, you'll come to do
the shorter time when you say one day. But if you said
one day and you do the longer time, what's that going to...
what problem is that going to lead to when you say today?
It won't lead to a problem.
I'm convinced it's a logical problem, but on רבי ירמיה's Rabbi Yirmiyah
mind is just the confusion of language. What I say one day...
yeah, but fine, but you'll never... what mistake will you make? So
you got a little confused, but there's no way if you say...
it
wouldn't lead to no prohibition anyway. It wouldn't lead to you doing
anything wrong. Okay. All right. So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
אמר רבינא אמר אמימר הכי אמר אבוך משמיה
דרב יוסף.
Amar Ravina
amar
Ameimar hachi amar avuch mishmei deRav Yosef. Here's what... so the גמרא's
Gemara not totally happy that that really all makes sense. When do
we start saying that when your time is up you still need
to get a היתר חכם, heter chacham, you know, because you'll confuse
it with another case? Like that's a little bizarre. So he says
listen, here's what your father told to me in the name of
רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. כמאן אזלא שמעתתא דרבי ירמיה בר אבא? Keman
azla shmaitata deRabbi Yirmiyah bar Abba? Who's the approach of רבי ירמיה
בר אבא Rabbi Yirmiyah bar Abba going like that says that even
when it gets to be nightfall you need to get a היתר
חכם? heter chacham? כרבי נתן. KeRabbi Natan. It's going like רבי נתן.
Rabbi Natan. דתניא, Detanya, we taught in a ברייתא. Baraisa. רבי נתן
אומר כל הנודר כאילו בנה במה והמקימו כאילו מקטיר עליה. Rabbi Natan
omer kol hanoder ke'ilu bana bamah vehamakaymo ke'ilu maktir aleha.
Anybody that makes a vow is like building a במה, bamah, and
if you fulfill it, it's like you burnt on it. So therefore
the way the ר"ן Ran explains it is we're not really so
concerned
that if you say today it's going to lead to... you know,
that when it's מותר at night it's going to lead to you
confusing it with another case. It's just that in general we don't
like vows. So since in general we don't like vows and there's
a little bit to be concerned about here, we're going to demand
you do a היתר חכם. heter chacham. Okay. Maybe also you could
say like in particular, maybe this was a way that people would
do, I'm just speculating here, but you know, this was like a
way that people would do little mini vows that would just sort
of... it maybe like particularly there was a sloppiness with this. Oh,
I'm going to do a vow for twenty-four hours, I'll do a
vow for three hours till the end of the day. Like this
would be where vows would more proliferate in these short little mini
vows. So therefore the rabbis are going to say, you know what,
we're going to make your life a little bit harder. And therefore
even if you say today, so if you say today, like that's
the most trivial of vows, right? It's like I'm fasting between snacks.
Okay. It's like I'm אסור assur until night for the next three
hours. So that's such a tiny little trivial vow, we're going to
make your life a little harder. We're going to demand come nightfall
you do a היתר חכם. heter chacham. So the ר"ן Ran says
like it's some combination of the two. There's a little bit to
be concerned about that if we're lenient in this, if we let
you do it without a היתר חכם, heter chacham, maybe you'll be
lenient in another case. But ultimately it's driven by the idea that
we're not thrilled with vows altogether.
But there's nothing to be concerned about like I said, I won't
drink wine until twelve PM tomorrow, they wouldn't need a היתר חכם,
heter chacham, right?
Correct, correct. Okay, so now anyway the גמרא Gemara. says like this.
And by the way, a little practical thing in the ר"ן. Ran.
If you look in the ר"ן, Ran, five lines down in the
narrow lines, he says ומה שנהגו עכשיו בתענית יחידים דלא הוי אלא
מצפרא ועד פניא, U'mah she'nahagu achshav b'ta'anis yechidim d'lo havi ella m'tzafra
v'ad panya, right,
when you make a private תענית, ta'anis, you accept the תענית ta'anis
at מנחה mincha time, you're going to do your own private תענית,
ta'anis, okay, and it's אסור assur from daybreak until nightfall. ואפילו הכי
לכשתחשך שרי ליה בלא שאלה. V'afilu hachi l'chishecheshach shari lei belo she'eila.
And at nightfall you don't need a היתר חכם, heter chacham, right?
So why is that different? That's something that ends at nightfall and
we don't need a היתר חכם. heter chacham. ולא גזרו משום יום
אחד. V'lo gazru mishum yom echad. And we're not afraid that if
we allow that at nightfall then if you say one day we'll
be lenient similarly. היינו משום דהדבר ידוע שדינו של תענית כך היא.
Hainu mishum d'hadavar yadua shedino shel ta'anis kach hi.
Because everybody knows that a תענית ta'anis is one day and it's
over at nightfall and you know that you're in a תענית. ta'anis.
And you don't confuse that with a type of a vow of
I won't do X for a day. No, I'm in a תענית.
ta'anis. Everybody knows what's a תענית. ta'anis. A תענית ta'anis is something
that ends at nightfall like any such halakhic day that ends at
nightfall. Okay. כך היא ואין איסורו כשאר נדרים שכבר קבעו לו חכמים
זמן. Kach hi ve'ein issuro kish'ar nedarim shekevar kav'u lo chachamim zman.
Everybody knows that when you make a תענית, ta'anis, the תענית ta'anis
ends at nightfall, and you're not going to confuse being in a
תענית ta'anis with taking a vow not to do something.
Even though you accept a תענית Taanis through a vow, you're still
not making a נדר neder that all food is forbidden to you.
You're making a verbal acceptance of this thing called a תענית. Taanis.
And this thing called a תענית Taanis lasts until nightfall. And nobody's
going to confuse what I practice when I was practicing a תענית
Taanis with if I take a vow that's supposed to last for
the duration of a day. Okay? So there are some things that
do end at nightfall, but other things if you don't make a
תענית, Taanis, if you just say this is forbidden for the day,
we're going to make you do a התרת חכם hataras chacham even
after nightfall. Okay, so now the Gemara continues. That's the difference between
'for the day' where it's permitted at nightfall, but because we don't
like vows we make you do a התרת חכם, hataras chacham, as
opposed to saying 'for a day' which is 24 hours. Now, שבת
זו, Shabbos zu, continuing in the Gemara, this Shabbos, אסור בכל השבת
כולה. assur bechol haShabbos kula. So you're forbidden the whole week including
the coming Shabbos.
פשיטא, Pshita, that's obvious. מהו דתימא, Mahu d'teima, I might have thought
ימי דשבתא קאמר, yomei d'Shabta ka'amar, you mean the days of the
week, meaning you mean the week days. It's funny when you say
the days of the week, right, you don't think about Shabbos. You
say week days, right, week days as opposed to the weekend, right.
So maybe when you say Shabbos you mean only the week days,
okay, and maybe even though yes in principle Shabbos is part of
the week, we assume that wasn't on your mind when you're thinking
about week, you're thinking about the week days. קא משמע לן, Ka
mashma lan, that no, we say Shabbos is included when you say
the week, this week. Okay. חודש זה, Chodesh zeh, and אסור בכל
החודש, assur bechol hachodesh, ראש חודש הבא. Rosh Chodesh haba. This month
is the whole month, but Rosh Chodesh begins the next month and
it's not forbidden. פשיטא, Pshita, that's obvious. No, כי אצטריך לחודש חסר.
ki itzterich l'chodesh chaser. It's about that the month is lacking. Now
really it doesn't mean the month is lacking, it means this month
is full, the next month is lacking. The following month is that
we're talking about the Rosh Chodesh, that's lacking, right, because it normally
alternates, there are some exceptions, but normally alternates. So if the coming
month is a 29-day month, then the month you're in is a
30-day month. If it's a 30-day month, there are two days of
ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, right. Everybody knows how that works, right. The
first day of ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh is really day 30 of
the previous month. Okay, so in that case where you're in a
30-day month, so, so what's going to be the story about day
30? Okay.
מהו דתימא, Mahu d'teima, I might have thought ראש חודש לשעבר הוה,
Rosh Chodesh l'she'avar hava, and ולא ליתסר, v'lo litser, that the Rosh
Chodesh is of the, for the previous month. Now really it shouldn't
be ולא ליתסר, v'lo litser, it should really be ליתסר, litser, and
should be forbidden. Okay, so there's a, there are different גרסאות girsa'os
here. Okay, that the Rosh Chodesh belongs to the previous month and
should be forbidden because it's day 30. קא משמע לן, Ka mashma
lan, so this teaches you, no, קרי אינש קרי ליה ראש ירחא,
kari inish kari lei Rosh Yarcha, it's called Rosh Chodesh and therefore
it's assumed to belong to the following month, so that even though
you are, you say this month and technically day 30 is part
of this month, since we call it Rosh Chodesh and we, we,
we conceptualize it as part of the next month and therefore it
is not forbidden.
Even though Rosh Chodesh is part of the next month?
Yeah, exactly. Rosh Chodesh is part of the next month even if
it's really day 30. Okay, there's different גרסאות girsa'os in the Gemara
but we're going to go with that one. Now that leads to
an interesting הלכה למעשה halacha l'maaseh issue. I'm going to read it
in תוספות. Tosafos. ר"ן Ran discusses it also but it's clearer in
תוספות. Tosafos. If you take a look at תוספות Tosafos here in
the lower right hand corner on the wide lines at the bottom,
he says like this. אם כן, Im kein, two lines down in
the wide lines of תוספות Tosafos towards the end of the line,
כשכותבין כתובה, keshechosvin kesubah, when you write a kesubah, או שטרות, o
shtaros, or shtar, ביום ראשון של ראש חודש, beyom rishon shel Rosh
Chodesh, on the first day of a Rosh Chodesh of a two-day
Rosh Chodesh, what do you write? Right? So it's a two-day Rosh
Chodesh, what do you write? So and it's today is Rosh Chodesh
and you're writing a kesubah or a shtar or a get. So
what do you write? כותבין יום פלוני שהוא ראש חודש, kosvin yom
ploni shehu Rosh Chodesh, you say that they got married today on
Monday, Rosh Chodesh אדר, Adar, right. What was the month before אדר,
Adar, שבט? Shevat? מלא, malei, I
guess, I don't know this thing. Okay. Okay,
so anyway, so you say today ראש חודש אדר, Rosh Chodesh Adar,
okay, today Monday ראש חודש אדר, Rosh Chodesh Adar, even though really
it's the 30th of שבט. Shevat. Okay, but you say Monday, so
you know which day we're talking about, and you say Rosh Chodesh,
and you don't call it the 30th of שבט, Shevat, you call
it ראש חודש אדר. Rosh Chodesh Adar. Okay. כותבין יום
פלוני שהוא ראש חודש ואין צריך לכתוב יום שלושים, kosvin yom ploni
shehu Rosh Chodesh v'ein tzarich lichtov yom shloshim, you don't say it's
day 30 of שבט, Shevat, you say it's Monday ראש חודש אדר.
Rosh Chodesh Adar. דהכי משמע לן לקמן דתנן עד ראש חודש אדר
עד ראש חודש אדר הראשון ומדאמר בגמרא גבי שטר נדרים. dehachi mashma
lan l'kaman d'tanan ad Rosh Chodesh Adar ad Rosh Chodesh Adar Harishon
umid'amar b'gemara gabi shtar nedarim. So anyway, there's a Gemara later on
that discusses shtar neder. אלמא דין שטרות כדין נדרים, alma din shtaros
k'din nedarim, you go by the vernacular. So if we call it
ראש חודש אדר, Rosh Chodesh Adar, we're not calling it שבט Shevat
anymore, we're calling it ראש חודש אדר. Rosh Chodesh Adar. So you
have to say Monday ראש חודש אדר Rosh Chodesh Adar so it
shouldn't be confused with Tuesday ראש חודש אדר, Rosh Chodesh Adar, but
you don't mention
שבט. Shevat. Okay.
So meaning you don't say ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh at all? Just
say like the thirtieth day of שבט Shvat or whatever.
That's not what it's called. In the vernacular today is called the
first day of ראש חודש אדר. Rosh Chodesh Adar. Okay? כנדרים כבלשון
בני אדם. Kinedarim k'lashon bnei adam. Then he says פסק Psak and
now Michael will be
happy. ומיהו Umihu בגיטין begittin מהגט me'hagget which really makes a big
difference. Right? You don't want to be extra careful by a גט
get because that really determines if a woman's married or divorced. Okay,
טוב לכתוב שהוא יום שלושים לחודש טבת. Tov lichtov shehu yom shloshim
l'chodesh Tevet. Okay,
I wonder why he went from אדר Adar to טבת. Tevet. Anyway,
like, but okay, anyway, you write ראש חודש אדר שהוא יום שלושים
לחודש שבט. Rosh Chodesh Adar shehu yom shloshim l'chodesh Shvat. Alright, that's
what you would write. Okay, so you identify it both ways. It's
ראש חודש אדר. Rosh Chodesh Adar. That's true and that's how people
call it. But by the way, just be aware that it's also
day thirty of the previous month. וכן כתב רבינו תם בכתובת בתו,
V'chen katav Rabbeinu Tam b'chtubat bito, in his daughter's כתובה, ketubah, and
that's what we do in כתובות ketubot as well. We say ראש
חודש Rosh Chodesh X שהוא יום שלושים לחודש shehu yom shloshim l'chodesh
X. Okay, so interesting way he
said
you don't have to do that for a כתובה. ketubah. Right. You
only do it for a גט get and then he says רבינו
תם Rabbeinu Tam did it for a כתובה. ketubah. Exactly.
And that's what we do too.
Okay, that's what we do. Okay, back to the גמרא. Gemara שנה
זו אסור בכל השנה כולה. Shana zu assur bechol hashana kula. This
year is the whole year and ראש השנה Rosh Hashana is obviously
part of the next year. So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
איבעיא להו. Ibaia lehu.
They ask the question. Yeah, אמר, well yeah, I don't know why,
אמר קונם יין שאני טועם היום, Amar konam yayin she'ani to'em hayom,
מה דינו? mah dino?
If you don't say היום, hayom, today, or you don't say יום
אחד, yom echad, one day, you just say יום. yom.
Wine that I won't drink for day. I mean it's not even
grammatically correct. מה ההלכה? Mah hahalacha? כהיום, kehayom, is it like today,
או כיום אחד, o k'yom echad, or is it like one day?
You see the little letter by the one day which is going
to be the more מחמיר machmir position, which is what we're going
to what we're not going to actually פסקן, pasken, but we're going
to wind up in practice being more מחמיר machmir because we won't
know in the end. תא שמע, Ta shema, come and hear, ממתניתין.
mimatnitin. קונם יין שאני טועם היום. Konam yayin she'ani to'em hayom. It
says I won't today. אין אסור אלא עד שתחשך, Ein assur ela
ad shetechshach, it only goes till nightfall.
היום, Hayom, if you said something different like you just said day,
then כיום אחד דמי, k'yom echad dami, I would say that that
means a full day. It's only if you say היום hayom does
it mean today. Gemara says no, אימא סיפא, eima seifa, but the
end talks about look at the end. The end talks, the end
says that for to mean a full day you have to say
a full day. אמר יום אחד, Amar yom echad, if you say
one day, אסור מיום ליום, assur miyom l'yom, then you go for
twenty-four hours. היום, Hayom, if you didn't say one day, you just
said day, כהיום דמי, kehayom dami, it's like today. אלא מהא ליכא
למשמע מינה. Ela meha lika l'mishma mina. You can't hear from here
from here because the משנה Mishna does not say X and not
X. The משנה Mishna says X and Y. If you say X,
היום, hayom, it means it means till nightfall. If you say Y,
one day, it means twenty-four hours. It doesn't deal with everything that's
neither X nor Y. That's why we have our question. Okay, תא
שמע אמר רב אשי. Ta shema amar Rav Ashi. Says רב אשי,
Rav Ashi, תא שמע, ta shema, come and hear. קונם יין שאני
טועם השנה. Konam yayin she'ani to'em hashana. So we have a ברייתא
Beraita that says if you say wine is forbidden to me, right,
it's אסור assur to me for the year. נתעברה השנה אסור בה
ובעיבורה. Nitabra hashana assur bah u've'iburah. So if it becomes a a
month, a pregnant month, right, you get a second אדר, Adar, so
then the נדר neder continues through אדר Adar because it's still part
of the same year. Okay, by the way,
this Michael might be part of the חידוש chiddush about the ראש
השנה Rosh Hashana aspect, which says how do you would you define
the year? Does the year end at אדר, Adar, at the end
at ניסן Nissan or does the year end at תשרי, Tishrei, right?
Because you know according to the תורה, Torah, the year really ends
more the year cycles through and a new year begins in ניסן,
Nissan, right? I mean the identifying of תשרי Tishrei as ראש השנה,
Rosh Hashana, right, is I mean whatever there are different parts in
the תורה, Torah, right? The months are counted from ניסן, Nissan, the
years counted from תשרי. Tishrei. Anyway, okay, but anyway, right, so if
you think about it because the עיבור ibur year, the idea that
you have to include also the second אדר Adar is pretty obvious
if you're going to go through till the end of אלול. Elul.
Right, if it were to end at the end of אדר, Adar,
then you'd say oh no, it's not enough to end at the
end of אדר, Adar, you have to end at the end of
אדר שני. Adar Sheni. But actually if you go through ראש השנה
Rosh Hashana and you end at the end of אלול, Elul, of
course you're going to have to include an extra אדר Adar in
the middle. Okay, so that's what the ברייתא Beraita says. If you
say what?
Therefore you're saying the חידוש chiddush of the משנה Mishna was what?
We haven't said what the חידוש chiddush of the משנה Mishna was.
Oh, I mean me, I'm saying that maybe the חידוש chiddush of
the משנה Mishna, is that it means you go through ראש השנה,
Rosh Hashana, you don't go through till ניסן. Nissan. Okay, anyway, it
says קונם יין שאני טועם השנה נתעברה השנה אסור בה ובעיבורה. Konam
yayin she'ani to'em hashana nitabra hashana assur bah u've'iburah. So you also
can't you also have to include אדר שני Adar Sheni in your
נדר. neder. So the גמרא Gemara says היכי דמי? Heichi dami? What's
the case? אי אמר כדתני, Ei amar k'detani, if it's like the
ברייתא Beraita says, למה לי למימרא? lama li l'meimra?
So that's obvious. Meaning maybe part of the גמרא's Gemara question here
is exactly my point. Since the year goes until the end of
אלול, Elul, of course אדר שני Adar Sheni is going to be
included. If the year went to the end of אדר, Adar, we
could discuss whether אדר שני... Adar Sheni... is it obvious that אדר
שני Adar Sheni is included or not. But if the year goes
to the end of אלול, Elul, of course אדר שני Adar Sheni
is included. That would be obvious. אלא לאו, Ela lav, we're gonna
keep on going here, get a little ahead, דאמר שנה. de'amar shana.
It must be that the חידוש chiddush of this ברייתא braisa is
not the idea of the עיבור ibbur month itself, even though that
seems to be the focus of the ברייתא. braisa. The חידוש chiddush?
of the ברייתא braisa is you didn't say 'this year', you just
said 'year'. Okay? And the חידוש of the ברייתא braisa is when
you say 'year', you mean 'this year'. Okay? So אמר שנה כהשנה
דמי. amar shana kehashana damei. If you say year it means this
year. So we took a ברייתא braisa that wasn't talking about that
at
all, right?
It was talking about the חידוש of the idea of a leap
month, although again as the גמרא Gemara says it's quite obvious if
the year goes to the end of אלול. Elul. But anyway, and
we said no, the חידוש of the ברייתא braisa is that you
just said the word year. And that we interpret year to mean
this year. ויום נמי כהיום דמי. ve'yom nami kehayom damei.
And therefore if you said יום, yom, it would also mean not
24 hours, not a day, it would mean this day. So how
about that? Is that a good proof? גמרא Gemara says לא, lo,
לא, lo, לעולם דאמר השנה. le'olam de'amar hashana. The ברייתא braisa means
what it sounds like it's saying: you said 'this year'. So your
question was what's the חידוש? So מהו דתימא, mahu d'seima, I might
have thought הלך אחר רוב שנים, halach achar rov shanim, go after
most years, ולא אית ביה עיבור, velo is bei ibbur, and it
does not have an extra month most years. So therefore what? I
mean therefore it's again, it's bizarre. What's the הוה אמינא? hava amina?
Okay, most things don't so if I would go after most years,
I said 'this year', I would end because I got this extra
month thrown in, I would end at ראש חודש אלול Rosh Chodesh
Elul rather than ending at ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, you know, since
I did an extra month earlier. It's like a bizarre הוה אמינא.
hava amina. Anyway, so ולא אית ביה עיבור, velo is bei ibbur,
קא משמע לן kamashma lan that you have to live with the
fact that there's an extra month. Meaning the פשט pshat of the
ברייתא braisa is what the פשט pshat of the ברייתא braisa sounds
like: you said this year, you weren't expecting there to be an
extra month, there was an extra month, swallow it, live with it,
etc. Again, once the idea is that the year though ends at
the end of אלול, Elul, the idea that you're forced to accept
the extra month is much, much more obvious. So you do understand
what was bothering the גמרא. Gemara So we do not conclude what's
the story when you say something grammatically incorrect, when you say 'day'
as opposed to 'a day' or 'this day'. And because we don't
conclude, we wind up being מחמיר machmir and we'll translate when you
say 'day' to be 'a day' and 24 hours rather than 'this
day' which would end at nightfall.
Yes, so context to ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. So that implies that
on the second day of ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh you can't just
say ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, you have to say ראש חודש, Rosh
Chodesh, which is the first day of טבת. Tevet.
Well, no, maybe not because you mean if you because well it
would be obvious if you match up the day of the week.
If you say Tuesday, which is ראש חודש אדר, Rosh Chodesh Adar,
right, then you match up the day of the week and it's
technically correct because, right? Meaning the question is how could you say
Monday which is ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, which ראש חודש? Rosh Chodesh?
Day one or day two? So presumably it was assuming that because
of the day of the week, that would make it clear whether
it was ראש חודש יום, Rosh Chodesh yom, ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh,
what? In גיטין, Gittin, right, you would say, so then it would
be distinguished whether you said ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh which is the
30th of אדר Adar or you just said סתם ראש חודש. stam
Rosh Chodesh. But, yeah, I mean so you would use the other
pieces, you know, or what it's not saying to indicate. But it
gets, it gets confused, yeah. All right, so now we take on
to the next question. Let's see if we'll get to the end
of the דף today, the עמוד א. amud alef. So okay, איבעיא
להו, ibayei lehu, they asked a question: אמר יין שאני טועם יובל,
amar yayin shani toeim yovel, or here it says יובל yovel but
it could just say היובל. hayovel. And you didn't say a seven-year
cycle, you said for this 50-year cycle. Now again, it's not a
יובל, yovel, because then you would go 50 years back to the
same day. But no, for this יובל. yovel. When is this יובל
yovel over? Okay, so for this יובל, yovel, מאי? mai? שנת חמישים
כלפני חמישים או כלאחר חמישים? shenas chamishim kilifnei chamishim o kelachar chamishim?
When does this יובל yovel end? Does this יובל yovel end at
the beginning of the 50th year of the יובל yovel itself? Or
is the 50th year considered to be the end, the part of
this יובל? yovel? Right, which is not what we assume, right? I
mean you've got seven sevens, right, seven sevens, you've got seven sevens
and it ends here in a יובל, yovel, right? And then, you
know, we assume you start the next cycle of seven sevens, right?
Ending in a יובל. yovel. So the same way שבת, Shabbos, like
it's a week ending in a שבת, Shabbos, and we say this,
and we if these were days and that was a שבת, Shabbos,
we would say like that's the week, the week is the weekdays
leading up to שבת Shabbos and that's all part of the week.
So if you say I won't do it for this יובל, yovel,
is it for this, you know, 50-day unit? The יובל yovel is
the end of that period of time, so it would include the
יובל yovel year as well. Okay, do we say that or do
we say, right, that's the most obvious thing, or do we
say או כלאחר חמישים, o kelachar chamishim, maybe יובל yovel begins the
beginning of the next cycle? So תא שמע tasha shema come in
here. דתניא פלוגתא דרבי יהודה ורבנן, detanya plugta d'Rabbi Yehuda v'Rabbanan, it's
the דתניא detanya to the debate of Rabbi Yehuda and Rabbanan. between
Rabbi Yehuda and the Rabbis. וקדשתם את שנת החמישים שנה. Vekidashtem et
shnat hahamishim shana. You shall sanctify the 50th year. שנת חמישים אתה
מונה. Shnat hamishim ata moneh. You count the 50 years 50, right?
The Torah says שבע שבתות שנים, sheva shabbatot shanim, count 49 years.
So these are counted as 49 years and the 50th year is
counted as year 50. Okay, right? You shall sanctify the 50th year.
שנת חמישים אתה מונה ואי אתה מונה שנת חמישים ואחת. Shnat hamishim
ata moneh ve-ee ata moneh shnat hamishim ve-ahat. שנת חמישים ואחת. Shnat
hamishim ve-ahat. The verse says don't count it as 51. It's don't
count it as 50 and as one. Okay, what it's telling you
is this is 50, and the year after starts year one of
the next cycle. And do not say that this is year 50
and it's year one of the next cycle. Okay, you got it?
So this is 50 of the previous and afterwards starts a year
one.
A whole 50 year cycle,
full 50 year cycle,
as opposed to the end of the 50th year.
Right, right, and then 50 can be included in there. That's what
the חכמים Hachamim says. But רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says,
from here they said, יובל אינו עולה למנין שבוע. Yovel eino oleh
le-minyan shavua. Yovel does not count towards the seven years of the
next cycle. Okay, the next cycle starts with six years of planting
and a שמיטה year is a new seven years after year 50.
רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, Rabbi Yehuda says, יובל עולה למנין
שבוע, Yovel oleh le-minyan shavua, the Yovel counts to the beginning of
the next seven year cycle. So that's like שנת חמישים עולה לכאן
ולכאן. Shnat hamishim oleh le-chan u-le-chan. Okay, so year 50 he says
is 50 of the previous cycle and it's one of the next
cycle. And you have seven and seven and then... so basically according
to Rabbi Yehuda there would be 49 year cycles, right? The year
one of the next 49 year cycle is the Yovel year. So
this year you would only have five years of planting, right? You
wouldn't have six years of planting because the first year of the
cycle would be a Yovel year. So according to Rabbi Yehuda, if
you said "I won't drink, one is אסור assur the whole Yovel,"
so actually ironically, come the Yovel itself it would be permissible because
that already begins the next cycle. There are 49 year units, not
50 year units. Okay, it's just the first year of the next
unit is a Yovel year. So it's a very strange idea.
At the very beginning of the Yovel, right, according to this Yovel
cycle would be אסור assur to me, and it would include that
Yovel year up until the next...
exactly. אמרו לו, Amru lo, they said to him, to Rabbi Yehuda,
הרי הוא אומר, harei hu omer, the verse says שש שנים תזרע
שדך shesh shanim tizra sadecha that you plant your field for six
years, ואין כאן אלא חמש. ve-ein kan ela hamesh. According to you,
in this, the first year of a cycle of a, you only
have five years of planting because the Yovel year was אסור assur
and then you have five years of planting, so you only have
five years of planting.
So אמר להם, amar lahem, he said back to them, ולדבריכם, u-le-divreicham,
according to you, הרי הוא אומר, harei hu omer, וציוויתי את ברכתי
לשלוש השנים. ve-tziviti et birchati le-shalosh ha-shanim. It says that when you're
coming through, right, a שמיטה cycle, right, you have one... seven... sorry...
okay. So it says that the seeds will last for eight years...
for three years. Why for three years? Because you harvest your stuff
in year six. The stuff you harvest in year six has to
last you for part of year six, okay, all of year seven,
okay, and the beginning of year eight until you harvest it again.
So it says what you plant in the year six will last
for three years, not really three years, okay, not duration of three
years, but for during three years. Okay, it's very right. So he
says,
והרי כאן ארבע. ve-harei kan arba. He says to them, but that's
not always true. There's some years where you're going to need it
to last for four years because if this was the end of
a יובל Yovel cycle and year eight was a Yovel, the grain
from year six would have to last all the way into year
nine, right? Because you couldn't plant on year seven, on Shmita, you
couldn't plant on the Yovel, it would have to go... it would
have to go four years. So it's not always true that it's
just three years. אלא איכא לאוקמה בשאר שני שבוע. Ela ika le-ukma
bi-shear shenei shavua. Now the Gemara's talking, because you can tell it
switches to Aramaic. Okay, so really you would have to say when
the verse says for three years it's talking about a normal period
of time, you know, the other cycles, not when you're dealing with
a Yovel. When you're dealing with a normal Shmita without a Yovel.
So דידי נמי איכא לאוקמה בשאר שני שבוע. Didi nami ika le-ukma
bi-shear shenei shavua. So me too, you said, oh look here, you
only have five years of planting, you don't have six years of
planting. Fine, in that case, you only have five years of planting,
but when the Torah says you have six years of planting it's
talking about a normal scenario. Okay, normal scenario you have six years
of planting at the beginning of a cycle. The first year's a
Yovel, that's different, that's five years. But just because it doesn't work
one case... but just 'cause it doesn't work in one case in
the פסוק Pasuk does not mean that that's not the הלכה. Halacha.
Okay, so you have this fascinating debate whether year 50 counts in
both, you know, to the beginning of the next cycle or just
at the end of one, and the גמרא Gemara says that would
play out if somebody said this יובל. Yovel. Does it mean this
יובל, Yovel, does it include the יובל Yovel year itself, which is
obviously the פשט pshat that that's the end of this period, or
could it, רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, the יובל Yovel begins the beginning
of the next period, maybe it would, so the שבועה, shvuah, maybe
by coming יובל, Yovel, that would already be seen as the next
and that would be permissible. Okay, let's actually turn the page.
דף צ"ט עמוד ב'. Daf tzadik-tet amud bet.
Well it wasn't, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda was דחוי, dachuy, right, exactly.
Okay, so that would play out, that debate would play out if
you said האי יובל. Hai Yovel. עד הפסח, Ad HaPesach, if it's
forbidden to me until פסח, Pesach, it's אסור assur when פסח Pesach
arrives. But you said עד פני הפסח, ad pnei HaPesach, so רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir says it's when פסח Pesach begins, and רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda says, who was it, was it רבי יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda?
And רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi says it's when פסח Pesach leaves. למימרא,
Lemimra so what's that debate about? So you could say the debate
is about just what do the words mean? Okay, the גמרא in
קידושין Kiddushin says it's a debate about what the words mean, and
they say פני pnei can mean the face of פסח, Pesach, which
is the beginning, or the גמרא does an interesting thing, I said
maybe it means the front of the face or the back of
the face. The גמרא said that פני pnei may mean the word
פניא, panya, which means in Aramaic a word which means the, sort
of the evening of or the passing of פסח. Pesach. So maybe
פני pnei means the beginning of פסח, Pesach, the face, or maybe
it means the passing of פסח. Pesach. Maybe that's the debate. Okay,
it could be just a language debate. But the גמרא here wants
to say it's not a language debate, it's a different debate. Let's
see what the גמרא says. למימרא רבי מאיר סבר לא מעייל איניש
נפשיה לספיקא. Rabbi Meir savar lo ma'ayil inish nafshiah l'sfika. A person
does not want to get himself into doubtful territory. רבי יוסי סבר
מעייל איניש נפשיה לספיקא. Rabbi Yossi savar ma'ayil inish nafshiah l'sfika. A
person's prepared to get himself into doubtful territory. What does that mean?
It means that the word פני הפסח, pnei HaPesach, the face of
פסח, Pesach, is ambiguous. When does the face of פסח, Pesach, it's
the beginning, the middle, the end? Like everybody agrees that that's ambiguous.
So what do we assume you mean if you're using an ambiguous
term? So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says if you're using an ambiguous
term, you mean only until the point of non-ambiguity.
Right? So certainly I don't want to conclude any unclear part of
it. So clearly עד פני הפסח ad pnei HaPesach means until פסח
Pesach begins. Does it also go into פסח Pesach itself? Not clear.
So we're going to assume I didn't mean any part that wasn't
clear. Whereas רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi says no, maybe even though it
wasn't explicit and clear, it could mean that. Maybe you meant one
of the other possible meanings of that word, and maybe you meant
for it to go into the פסח Pesach itself. You're willing to
have your words mean some possibly ambiguous meaning. Okay. What?
I think he means the opposite. לא מעייל איניש נפשיה לספיקא. Lo
ma'ayil inish nafshiah l'sfika. Yeah, but רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi says it's
אסור... assur...
Wait, let's let him finish his thought.
Yeah, but the that a person would put themselves in a ספק
safek would mean that they hold עד פני הפסח ad pnei HaPesach
means the beginning of פסח. Pesach.
Why, how are you putting yourself in a ספק? safek?
If, well, the ספק safek period is the
פסח Pesach itself, right?
So if you say I'm not going to put myself in a
ספק, safek, that means I want to include פסח Pesach because I
don't want to have any unclear part.
Oh, that's how I don't want to put myself in a ספק,
safek, I want to be, I want to avoid being עובר over
on a ספק. safek. Yeah, but we're talking not like,
right, I hear the point. But anyway, that's not how the גמרא
is interpreting it. It's talking about like whether you are, whether you
want your words to place you into that zone or not. So
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says I don't want to ever enter into
that zone, so I'm going to say my words don't mean that,
you know. All right, so the גמרא says like this, רמיניה, Reminihi,
I'll ask you on this. We have the reverse. מי שיש לו
שתי כיתי בנות, Mi she'yesh lo shtei kitei banot, somebody has two
groups of daughters. משתי
נשים, Mishtei nashim, so somebody's married two wives. Okay, somebody, אברהם Avraham
is married שרה Sarah and קטורה. Keturah. And from each of his
wives he has two daughters, an older daughter and a younger daughter.
ואמר, Ve'amar, and he says קדשתי את בתי הגדולה. Kidashti et biti
ha'gedolah.
I married my older daughter. I said to somebody, I said you
want to marry one of my daughters? He says sure. Which one?
It doesn't matter which one. Fine, okay, I'll marry you my older
daughter. So what do you mean by older?
Okay, ואיני יודע אם גדולה שבגדולות אם גדולה שבקטנות אם קטנה שבגדולות.
Ve'eini yodei'a im gedolah she'ba'gedolot im gedolah she'ba'ketanot im ktanah she'ba'gedolot. I
don't know. It sounds like maybe he didn't know at the time
who he was marrying, but he doesn't remember. But actually the way
we're going to interpret it, it means he said my older daughter,
and we don't know what those words mean. Does it mean the
older daughter of the older of the first wives? Or does it
mean the older daughter of the second wife? Or maybe it even
means the younger daughter of the first wife? Because that could still
be called גדולה gedolah because she's my daughter from the older wife,
okay, from the first wife. Okay. כולן אסורות, Kulan assurout, so since
your words can mean any one of those three possibilities of the
four, all those daughters are ספק safek married. דברי רבי מאיר, Divrei
Rabbi Meir, חוץ מן הקטנה שבקטנות. chutz min ha'ktanah she'ba'ketanot. The only
one girl it couldn't have meant is the younger daughter from the
younger wife. רבי יוסי אומר כולן מותרות חוץ מן הגדולה שבגדולות. Rabbi
Yossi omer kulan mutarot chutz min ha'gedolah she'ba'gedolot. No, we'll interpret your
word to only mean... the narrowest possible meaning of the word. And
the גדולה gedola will mean the narrowest possible meaning will be the
older daughter of the older wife.
Okay, אזיל אינשי בתר שמיה. azil inshi batar shme. Right.
So this is the reverse. Okay, Rabbi Meir
said your words could include some of the ambiguous possibilities, and Rabbi
Yossi says your words are only going to include the one thing
that it most definitely means.
Okay, so that's the absolute reverse of what they said of whether
מילי דאינש נפשיה וספיקא. milei de'inish nafshieh usfeika. So אמר רבי חנינא
בר פפא אמר רב, amar Rabbi Chanina bar Pappa amar Rav, מוחלפא
השיטה. muchlefa hashita.
You're right, we got the names reversed. In our משנה, Mishna, which
daughter you're מקדש, mekadesh, exactly. In our משנה, Mishna
Rabbi Meir would say that it includes the doubtful times and Rabbi
Yossi would say that it would not. Okay, ותניא, tanya, we taught
a ברייתא Braisa that actually does reverse the names: זה הכלל, zeh
haklal, כל שזמנו קבוע, kol shezmano kavua, ואמר עד פני. ve'amar ad
pnei.
If you have a fixed time, we'll get back to what that
means tomorrow, and you said פני, pnei, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir אומר
omer עד שיצא, ad sheyeitzei, it includes the entire duration until the
entire time is over. רבי יוסי אומר Rabbi Yossi omer עד שיגיע,
ad sheyagia, no, it only goes until the time begins. So there
you have it, we've got a ברייתא Braisa that reverses, that says
Rabbi Meir says it goes through פסח Pesach and Rabbi Yossi says
it only goes up until פסח. Pesach. So we're going to go
based on this משנה in קידושין Kiddushin and say that when you
say a phrase that's ambiguous, Rabbi Meir includes the ambiguous meanings and
Rabbi Yossi does not include the ambiguous meanings.